howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show this is a current episode
currents are shorter and less heavily
produced than our full-length episodes
and generally focus on a single topic as
always links to books articles and
organizations mentioned are available on
the episode page at Jim read show calm
that's Jim rut show calm today's guest
is Chris console ease professor of
astrophysics at the University of
Nottingham in the UK hi Jim great to be
here really good to have you here we're
gonna talk about something that
listeners to the show know that I'm very
interested in which is is there
intelligent life in the universe
actually in this case we're gonna be
talking about is there communicating
extraterrestrial intelligence Chris and
his co-author damn I don't have your
co-authors name in front of me why don't
you tell me your co-authors name the
co-author was Tom Westby and he is the
first author and he's the one who took
really the the lead in writing the paper
and doing the analysis I was more of his
supervisor he's a master student who
works in engineering at the University
of Nottingham and in mathematics he's
like a kind of like a lecturer type
position there where he does quite a bit
of teaching and he was interested in
doing a project in astronomy with me and
on this this project on
asking about how many communicating
intelligent civilizations they are is
not really something that let's call it
mainstream astronomy it would some time
to prove up or do and so someone who
wanted to do like a terminal degree it's
a masters would be the best person to do
this kind of project because he's not
interested in having a full-time career
as an astronomer and I'm already
established so they can't get rid of me
so easily I love it's kind of like in
cognitive science speculation about
consciousness has that same attribute
you better wait till you get your Nobel
Prize or at least till you're a tenured
professor to ever to say the c-word or
you'll be in big trouble alright
fortunately that's starting to break
down I hope SETI becomes a legitimate
more legitimate field and what we had
Jill tarter on the show back in
September and of course she spent her
whole life fighting against the
prejudiced against both females her
honors and SETI and has done done lots
of very interesting work that's it
anyway the paper we're gonna talk about
today was recently published by Chris
and his co-authors called the
astrobiological Copernican weak and
strong limits for intelligent life it's
published in the Astrophysical Journal
but for most of us getting it off the
archive server is just fine a pre-press
version a little ugly but it's
definitely readable then as always we'll
post a link to that article on the
episode page at Jim ratio calm again as
listeners to the show now I am
absolutely fascinated with this question
about extraterrestrial life in fact my
own personal hierarchy of scientific
questions I ranked it number 2 people
say well what's your number one and my
number one is why is there something and
not nothing you know why does the
universe even exist and like SETI that's
considered a somewhat out-of-bounds
question in some of the more established
fields of science that's alright but
number two is are we alone
has so many huge implications about you
know what is the purpose of humans on
earth you know what is our destiny
what's the destiny of the universe just
gigantic question
and this is a question people have been
speculating about for a long time and
Chris and team have done something which
is very interesting which is they've
taken the old Drake Equation and they've
updated it with a lot of the new
findings and science we're gonna go over
here a little bit and they've used a
interesting I'll argue with them a
little bit about the the the
appropriateness of it but this weak and
strong Copernican principle and then and
it yields some you know specific numbers
on how many what's the range of the
number of communicating civilizations
within our galaxy so with that I'm gonna
turn it over to Chris to may be frame a
little bit about the history of the
Drake Equation you know and some of the
insights on new scientific discoveries
that have allowed you to restate it in a
in a different perhaps more tractable
fashion sure thanks very much right so
essentially the way to look at this
problem is really to in some ways take
it from a historical perspective so for
many thousands of years people have
wondered about life on other planets and
other places within our galaxy within
the universe and they have actively
speculated on this for as long as really
we've been able to write so we know the
ancient Greeks thought about this and we
know that throughout time since then
that it's also been a major question
people were burned at the stake for for
suggesting it and it's been highly
controversial throughout time and simply
because we just don't know and we still
don't know we don't have an answer and
my paper doesn't tell us an answer
either it just gives us some benchmark
for how to measure measure this question
and what the potential answer might be
within a few assumptions so with that
for let's say a couple hundred years or
so in the past from now the astronomers
that thought about this question we're
quite bullish on the idea that there is
life throughout even the solar system so
for example strana murders like William
Herschel and his son John Herschel two
of the most distinguished astronomers at
the turn of the 19th century both
believed that
that many of the planets and even the
Sun and the moon were inhabited that
there was life throughout our solar
system and in fact of course you have
Percival Lowell and the canals on Mars
which was a huge topic at the turn of
the 20th century with many many
astronomers believing this of course
there were doubts in that time but
throughout the 20th century as we've
learned more and more about the solar
system we have realized that life at
least intelligent life certainly doesn't
really or cannot exist let's say within
our solar system that we are really the
only intelligent species within our
solar system it would be hard to believe
that they could be so well hidden that
we wouldn't have seen anything by now
and that of course happened when you had
the space probes going to to Mars
landing on Mars Venus and so on and we
know that there's no you know
civilizations living on Mars building
canals that's certainly not true and
there is a need even even evidence for
any kind of past life on Mars that's
convincing I would think so far so much
up there just with one little pushback
which is you know there is some thinking
that they're you know that there could
be life maybe even intelligent life
though probably not communicating at
least well I don't know about that on
some of the couple of the icy moons
Europa what's the other one around
Saturn but anyway there's two of them
that's thought that we'll have water
oceans well under the surface that could
be liquid water and we'll have rocky
bottoms so they'll provide the metallic
ions that are necessary for our kind of
life yeah we could have something like
octopuses or something like that down
there and who knows once you know how
far what they might have been able to
develop so I wouldn't quite rule it out
in the solar system yet it is to my mind
one of the very key questions that will
actually help get some traction on the
part of the Drake Equation that you more
or less punted on which is is life does
it happen all the time does it happen
never almost never you know fairly often
but a random roll of dice and you know
looking at those undersea environments
may provide us a big clue on that but
anyway continue sorry for the
interruption no no no please
Center up much as you like yeah so what
you said is is true what what I perhaps
should have said in a clearer way is
that there isn't a intelligent
communicating life within the solar
system that we would have detected that
unless the way they communicate is very
different from the way that we do and
that's hard to imagine how that might be
so what I mean by that is there's not
like these octopi or not you know they
don't have like under underwater cities
that have that emit light or have radio
waves or something because we would have
detected that by now so that's what I'm
what I really meant by that so you're
absolutely right that these moons could
indeed have some form of life in them
and I certainly would not want to
discourage people from thinking about
that considering that or and searching
for it and having missions to go look
for it I think all that's very good and
should be done but I do think that that
it would be hard to imagine that there
would be intelligent communicating life
on on those moons but hey if I'm wrong
that would be fantastic right that'd be
great okay so that's really the the kind
of the history up into the 20th century
for this idea of looking for let's say
life went on other parts of the universe
and it's always been something which has
been solar system focused people really
want to know about it in the solar
system people want to know and find out
life in the sources and it's really been
the focus for a very long time and
personally I think that when we noticed
that life wasn't super common at least
in the solar system that people got very
discouraged about this idea of there
being any kind of life throughout the
universe simply because we weren't
finding it in places where we once
thought it might exist of course SETI
happen
at about the same time and SETI's is a
little bit different from looking for
life in the solar system because the
traditional SETI looks for radio waves
coming from other stars which may be
produced by an intelligence something
which cannot be produced by a known
Astrophysical object or process which
emits light in a way that we understand
you have to find a signal which looks
artificial that is looks made by an
elected by an intelligence and that
started in around 1960 and since then
these the SETI surveys have gotten more
sophisticated and bigger and you have
various big projects going on now to
look for SETI in this way and that's
fantastic so the question that we wanted
to answer and this is something that
I've been thinking about for for a long
time for almost well 10 years now is can
we actually say something about the
number of likely communicating
intelligent civilizations that are in
the galaxy that we could detect right
now
so there's a lot to pick apart with with
that statement so you have to have life
that's that's the first thing and then
you have to also have intelligent life
that's the second thing but then you
also have to have communicating
intelligent life so you have to have all
three of those for this calculation to
work okay so if you have intelligent
life so we've had intelligent life on on
earth for for a very long time for you
know maybe a hundred thousand years or
so maybe more than that and we've had
communicating intelligent life for only
about a hundred years that is that's how
long we on earth as humans have been
artificially producing signals from the
earth which got into space okay and you
can think of this as radar as radio
waves from radio from television from
satellites or even lights that come from
cities so those are artificial
reproductions of artificial light which
is not produced by an Astrophysical
process is produced by an intelligence
the communicating intelligence so that's
what we mean by that and so we know
that's existed on earth for about a
hundred years okay
now the other thing which happened in
the last decade is that we've learned a
lot about about galaxies about star
formation about planets where we can
start really answering this question of
how many of the type of communicating
extraterrestrial civilizations might
there be throughout our galaxy and the
way we approach this problem was very
simple we just said let's assume that
that life intelligent life and even a
communicating intelligent life is a
natural process which happens in science
so this is a big question of course and
you know we could very well be wrong
I completely admit this but we have no
idea if it's right or wrong so I would
argue it's important to make that
assumption and to look at what you find
so the question is how many of these
exists throughout our galaxy how many of
these communicating extraterrestrial
civilizations are there so let's just
assume that they just form as a natural
part of science for example if you have
the right amount of gas at the right
temperature and density you form a star
or form a galaxy you form different
things that you see in science are
produced in a way which is predictable
based on the initial conditions of of
how you start so why should life be any
different than that so this is really
the way that I like to think about it
and this is the assumption that we make
in this calculation we'll come back to
this again about testing that assumption
when said he actually succeeds and let's
say Maps the galaxies in terms of it's
intelligent life within it ok so what do
you need to know to do this calculation
you need to know how many stars are as
old as the Sun you need to know how many
of those stars can survive that long so
the Sun is about about five billion
years old how many other stars that are
existing in our galaxy today are at
least that old and it's actually a
pretty high fraction it's in the 90s the
percentage of stars that are in our
galaxy today are potentially able to
host life in terms of his age so that
doesn't really just qualify very many
stars then you have the idea of how many
of these stars have planets and this is
something which has always been a big
unknown and you mentioned this already
the Drake Equation is is how many stars
have planets and this is something that
we actually have some idea about now
from the Kepler
which is a satellite mission which which
observed a patch of sky to look for
planets around stars and was able to say
there's about seventeen eighteen percent
of stars have planets in the habitable
zone in the habitable zone is that area
around the star which is not too hot
which is not too cold which is able and
principal to form life as we know it on
earth that is the same temperature is
roughly the Sun at the at the surface of
the earth so with those two things you
now know how many stars there are you
know how many planets there are around
each Sun but at the same time another
feature which was never part of the
original Drake Equation is answering the
question well how does the metallicity
of the stars change throughout the
galaxy so the metallicity is really
critical for this I think and the reason
is well first of all let me explain what
metallicity is so metallicity to an
astronomer is any element which is
heavier than helium so that kind of is
sometimes funny to people when I when I
teach this and in my classes and I tell
students this they sometimes laugh
because it sounds ridiculous and I think
it did to me once too but this is the
way his try numbers talk so metals are
anything heavier than helium in the
periodic table so elements like he
carbon oxygen nitrogen the big ones you
need for life are all what astronomers
called metals and these all sort of
correlate together that is when you find
a star that has a lot of carbon you also
find a lot of oxygen and nitrogen and so
on they go together because they're
formed in nucleosynthesis in in stars
which then go supernova and go through
stellar evolution which then reproduces
these elements into the interstellar
medium which then use for further star
formation so they correlate together so
what you need essentially getting to the
point of this is that you need a star
that has a high metal content that is
has a loss of these elements to form
life because you can't make life as far
as we know it out of just hydrogen
helium doesn't exist and it's hard to
imagine how that could ever happen if
you want things like amino acids these
kind of things you need to have these
these elements that were heavier than
you know
so the places of in our galaxy where you
have these these heavier elements are
more likely to form life and that is
also something that's has only been
known in the last 5 years or so and so
we know how many stars have the right
metal content by the way the Sun our own
star is pretty metal rich compared to
most stars on our galaxy
it is much richer than most most nearby
stars at least in our own galaxy and
that may or may not have anything to do
with the fact that we exist at all
but I think it does I think you need to
have these heavy elements and you need
to have them in great abundance to
actually produce life ok so putting all
that together you can then ask well how
many of these stars have planet which
can host life potentially in the
habitable zone how many of them have the
right metal content and when you do that
what you need to den calculate is how
long you think these intelligent
communicating civilizations will last
and this is really one of the key
aspects of this and one of the funnest
parts of it and will hopefully hopefully
we can get into this in more detail but
essentially it's how long do you think
the civilizations will last this has
always been one of the big unknowns
within the Drake Equation and the simple
thing that we did was was one of the
things we did was to just assume that
the life which exists which is
communicating is similar to our own and
we know that we've been around for a
hundred years sending out signals into
space so we just ask the question well
what if these other civilizations only
last 100 years and we know that we've
lasted 100 we may go longer we may go
hopefully go longer but you know we may
go 200 years a million years we don't
know but we know we've done a hundred so
let's just see if we use a hundred as
the typical average lifespan of a
intelligent communicating civilization
how many would you expect to find so we
put all that together what we find is
that you have on average about 36 and
then if you look at the error range in
that which is important based on the
errors on these values you find that the
error goes from a couple to up to about
200 so that's really the range of what
you would expect based on this
assumption
about how life forms within our galaxy
if you think life forms in our galaxy
around other stars in a similar way as
it does on our own that is that life and
intelligent life is not outside of the
let's say scientific process of forming
structure and and and how science works
then this is really how many you would
expect to see based on a lifespan which
is similar to our own at the current age
now if you want to believe that that the
lifespan of an average civilization is
much longer than a hundred years then
you can usually use our formula and
calculate how many you would expect and
that number would go up but this is sort
of a lower limit if you will based on
this assumption okay let me ask a couple
of clarifying questions about one in
your paper you let you lay out two
different models the weak and the strong
Copernican principle as I recall from
the paper 36 is for the strong
Copernican principle is that correct yes
and if you could maybe make the
distinction between the strong and the
weak and provide people what the number
might be for the weak principle Yeah
right that's a great question so the
strong principle is that life forms
exactly the same way as it has on earth
so that just means that essentially that
life will form around five billion years
and the errorbar that we put on that is
about a billion years so we allow life
to form between 4.5 and 5.5 billion
years that is that that's when life will
that elegent life that communicating
intelligent life will appear within that
limited range of time the weak principle
is that it takes five billion years at
least to form a communicating
intelligent life so that life can
conform at five billion years six
billion years seven billion years all
the way up to the age of the the start
because obviously you can't have life
forming in a star over a time period
which is older than the stars age so the
stars age is like upper limit to how
long that life can form so that gives
you a lot more time for the life to form
within the within the star and when you
use that you find that there's a couple
thousand possible of these these these
communicating extraterrestrial
intelligence telogen to outer galaxies
which we call Chetty with the sea that's
what we call them and so it's slightly
different so depending on how you assume
things will form that's what you would
that's what you would find if you only
use this five billion years or so as
a lower limit for the amount of time it
takes for this communicating intelligent
civilization to form gotcha
and just for the audience's sake the the
median age of stars in the galaxies what
about 10 billion years as I recall it's
it's in our paper I'm no I'm gonna say
it wrong fortunately but it's it I think
it's around 9 my mercury actually you
have the median age as 10.35 about that
10.35 ok sorry it sounds a little bit
off so it's it's about five gears yeah
the mean age is a bit lower Knapp though
we know that a lot of there's that skew
down at the low end for the giant stars
yeah so yeah the media it's about 10
this call it's called 10 close enough
another question I had that you didn't
address is that I recall from the course
in stellar evolution or actually as part
of an astronomy of course I took it I
was in college that the supernovas were
much more common in the earlier days
than today with that in any way change
your analysis no we didn't consider that
and the reason we didn't is because
supernovae certainly are more common
when you have more star formation events
and those will have occurred let's say
billions of years ago so the star
formation in our galaxy peaked about 3
or 4 billion years after the Big Bang
and now we are almost 14 billion years
after the Big Bang so there was a long
time ago when the peak of star formation
occurred and those supernovae would have
happened within a couple hundred million
years of this you know when the star
formation happens so most supernovae and
our galaxy would have occurred much
earlier in its history and you have to
be pretty close to a supernova for to
really affect the life on the on the
planet so it's probably not a major
production or destruction of of these
life-forms within our galaxy especially
when we know the rate is about I'm gonna
say it wrong but the rate is I think
only maybe a couple a century at most
for these supernovae happening within
our own galaxy and they're not
necessarily the type which come about
and star formation but are the the type
one supernova which are thought to be
produced by gas and falling out to like
a neutron star or black hole
those are are also pretty pretty rich in
energy but again they're not really that
common throughout our galaxy sister
galaxy's history today at least and so
if you have a civilization that
typically can last a couple hundred
years you have these supernovae
happening maybe a few a century at most
it's very unlikely that they're going to
be so close that they would totally
destroy that civilization yeah I was
thinking more as a source of metals
right now I think our Sun is thought to
be what at least a third generation star
maybe maybe more and unusually late and
that there was a supernova not that long
before the Sun formed that seeded it
with an unusual may maybe maybe an
unusual rich assortment of higher atomic
weight elements well that's a really
good question is how many supernovae
produced the elements that we use on
earth that made up our solar system and
that's kind of a tricky thing to know
it's probably not just one I think I'm
pretty sure it's not just one it
probably is a collection of a mini over
you know eons of time happening right so
that the Sun the Sun formed in our own
galaxy about eight billion years after
the galaxy was born so you've had eight
billion years of evolution and and star
formation and supernova happening which
can produce tons of these kind of metals
which the solar system formed from so
it's not just one supernova but it's
likely to be very many you know got it
all right let's go also let's talk about
this key number L which yeah is you know
again what you know why I thought I
think it's so interesting to tell us
about ourselves and our destiny L being
the average length of a communicating
intelligent civilization or space call
it species it may not have a
civilization but that's called a species
that is able to broadcast at least for
these purposes radio waves out into
space and you know one thing that's
important to note is that if we use
radio waves as the metric there's two
ways this radio waves could stop being
emitted one is the civilization loses
the capacity let's say it collapses
either from a natural cause like an
asteroid or an endogenous cause like
you know a nuclear war or and this is
one and you know in the study of the
Fermi paradox comes up quite a bit is
maybe they stopped music radio waves and
I use something else you know they use
gravity waves or neutrino beams or even
directed laser beams some other form of
communications that at least today we
would we would have it difficult to
track though I do know from
conversations with people in the city
world they are now starting to think
about how to detect point-to-point laser
communication yeah I mean there's a lot
a lot to say about L right that's really
one of the key things and you're
absolutely absolutely right to say that
it tells us about about ourselves so one
day when SETI actually studies the
entire galaxy and it won't be anytime
soon but let's say they know let's say
they know for sure that there's no life
within within our galaxy at all that's
existing right now that we can detect
now let's assume that they also have
rolled out these things about neutrinos
and gravitational waves and stuff and
that we know for sure that there's no
other life in the galaxy
well that would tell us a couple of
things it would tell us that either the
lifespan of the civilizations on average
is very short or it would tell us that
we are indeed very unique in terms of
our formation and that our formation is
sort of outside of a natural progression
of science but is more of a random thing
which which happened in in some random
way right maybe life is just something
which you know you just just so happens
right it doesn't happen that by nature
so to speak but just develops sort of on
its own in its own way in a way that we
don't really understand so the other
thing is is that if let's say SETI
succeeds and we start finding lots of
these civilizations let's say close to
us
so with this thirty-six number I talked
about the typical distance to those
civilizations will be about seventeen
thousand light-years away which is
really far and they'd be really hard to
detect the signal coming from any of
those kind of of civilizations but
simply because of the distance and the
signal would be very weak by the time it
got to us but let's say you you have
detected with SETI many civilizations
through
our galaxy let's say you know within our
own local universe where if SETI exists
in great abundance that's where you'd
find it first because simply that's just
these years to find then they would
really tell us something about El it
would tell us that L must be quite long
that the average lifespan of an
intelligent communicating civilization
in our galaxy the lifetime of that is
quite long and that would be really good
news for our own existence assuming that
these creatures are similar to us and
the way that we have technology and the
way that we can destroy ourselves the
way that we can be destroyed as you say
by asteroids or by other parts of
astronomy let's say supernovae gamma-ray
bursts etc so that would really be
something great for us to learn not just
about existence of life that exists
throughout the galaxy and other places
but also that actually we may have a
chance of figuring out how to survive
and on our own planet for a very long
time to come and that I think would be a
great thing to know as well so it tells
us not only about how where we came from
but it tells us where we're going and
how long we might actually be around so
SETI is important for both of those
things it's really important to tell us
if we're alone but also tells us
something about where we might be going
into the future and where we actually
did come from so it's really answering
really fundamental questions but I'd
like to come back to the this idea of
gravitational wave and neutrino physics
and stuff being used as sort of a more
difficult way of transmitting I find it
hard to believe that if a civilisation
arose throughout the galaxy and was
intelligent and was able to develop
technology that they wouldn't have some
kind of phase where they actually were
using similar technology that we do like
electromagnetic radiation which is super
common throughout the whole universe and
it's an easy way to communicate easy way
to transmit information etc and it'd be
very hard to imagine that a civilization
would go from being you know
not technological to having you know
gravitational wave communication that
would be almost impossible to believe so
there must be some phase where they're
actually doing some kind of
electromagnetic transmission and it's
being possible to have that not escape
from its host planet out into space so
looking for that kind of thing I think
is still a very valuable thing to keep
pertaining to do now one of the
criticisms I have with SETI is I don't
think that these intelligent
communicating civilizations actually
necessarily want to be found
and I don't think they're sending out
huge radio signals to be found it's
something that we would have to detect
just based on whatever they're sending
out to each other and we just happen to
catch a glimpse of it you know through
our own our own mechanisms but but but
not necessarily something that was meant
for us to see so and that's going to be
very hard to do because why would they
send out a big signal on their own
planet that we would need actually
detected ourselves why would they send
out that signal so we got to really look
for very very faint signals which is why
SETI looking in the radio it's going to
be really difficult to do for more
distant objects this is outside the
focus your paper but something we've
talked about before with other guests is
exactly this question what's called Medi
messaging extraterrestrial intelligence
you know there are a group of people who
are advocating that the human race start
to broadcast to the world or to the
universe to the galaxy at least hey
we're here and then there's another
faction very strongly argues that would
be the stupidest thing in the world
right because you know using some
evolutionary arguments it's possible
that if interstellar travel wherever
possible predator species may be more
common than prey species and that - you
know yell out we're here until we know
what's going on in the galaxy might be
really dumb the ebony if you have an
opinion on the Metis controversy yeah so
of course you know I have people who
email me now daily saying that they they
do many all the time but of course
so they think that being communicating
with aliens now you'd be amazed at some
of the emails I get you probably buy
their dental fillings right yeah to
friend asking more details some of these
messages are very exactly the the
communication with these other
civilizations I think would be really
hard to do not just because of the
distances I think this goes to the Fermi
paradox to some degree if we get to that
is that these great distances make it
really almost impossible to communicate
so if you have a something 17,000
light-years away and we detect them and
we send off a signal to them when we
detect them saying hello you know
welcome to earth or whatever then we
take 17 thousand years to get to them
and then if they reply we take 17
thousand years to get back right because
speed of light is is constant so that
would take thirty-four thousand years
for us to receive an answer to our
message which is you know that's a
really long time it's hard to imagine
that but at the same time if the
lifetime of those civilizations is only
a few hundred years or even a few
thousand years then there would be long
gone by the time our signal would reach
them so we really even could not
communicate even if they could detect
our signal and could understand it and
then send an answer back that we could
understand they would be long gone so
you have to have combination of being
close by but also having the long long
lifetime of civilizations now this whole
idea about being scared of aliens and
not wanting to transmit our our
information about our existence I think
is wrong I think the reason for that the
reason it's wrong is that if any kind of
alien civilization is is so highly
technical that they could come to us and
say and potentially destroy us which
they probably could if they were able to
transmit that that amount of space that
civilization must be very advanced much
more advanced than ours
so they really have been around much
longer than we have I won't speculate
how long but let's say you know
thousands millions of years longer than
we've
then developing our technology so they
have all kinds of technology which is
incredible I'm sure but at the same time
they've also had to manage to find a way
to to not destroy themselves that is
they found a way where they they haven't
you know done the equivalent of nuclear
war or had you know global warming
destroy everybody or you know found a
way that to get people to wear masks
when they have like Coke ovid type this
Hesper going on like we do now so that
not everyone just dies dies away so
they've managed to figure that out and
that takes I think some sophistication I
think this is something that our own
species still needs time to develop is a
sophisticated way of being able to live
together to survive for longer than a
few hundred years with a high degree of
technology and this would be a challenge
for humans in the coming centuries is
how how do we manage this we've already
had to deal with it of course in the
last hundred years and it's only going
to get worse with things like AI and who
knows what else is coming up so they've
managed to do that so I would like to
think that they have and maybe this is
just me being crazily optimistic is that
they've managed a way to have a a
philosophy or a sort of a the way they
look at the universe the world and ever
other living creatures perhaps is that
you know they're not there to be
destroyed but they're there to somehow
live and some kind of you know harmony
or or whatever you know what have you in
terms of not just destroying things but
finding a way to be peaceful to manage
things better so that's the way I like
to think of it now I could be wrong so
if you know if an alien does come out on
lands on earth I certainly wouldn't want
to be the first person to come talk to
it but that's the way that you know I
like to see it and and I think that the
the reason that they could survive so
long that they must have a way of
understanding that destruction is not a
good way of keeping their civilization
afloat so that that's kind of how I see
that one and actually that's may
actually be an argument to urgently send
out many messages I mean it looks like
we have lots of ways to kill ourselves
maybe it's a lifeboat made a message hey
we're about that blow our planet up I
nuclear weapons or fry ourselves or let
loose nanobots that turn the planet into
gray goo or something how is there was
anybody else out there that managed to
get past all these traps please tell us
how you did it of course for your
calculation it might be 17,000 years
before we got the answer in which case
it may well be too late in fact actually
I had a thought when you were saying
that that there's another calculation
you could do from your calculations
I would encourage your student to do
this which is that let's say you set a
parameter that you want to civilizations
to be able to do at least five round
trips to be able to exchange their
knowledge and touch points and translate
each other's languages etc there is some
El which will then create a probability
map of how big does El have to be to
have a 50% chance say of there being a
civilization for which you could have
five round trips I know you can derive
that from the numbers that you guys have
put together I'd encourage you guys to
do that it would be very very
interesting does El have to be a hundred
thousand to be able to have a high
enough density what's a cool thing about
your calculations as the longer el is
the higher the density is and therefore
the more round trips you can have both
because they're closer and because L is
longer they don't blow up while you're
trying to have the round trip so that
would be kind of a fun number to
calculate yeah and it might actually
tend to rule out a tight-knit well I
don't know what it would tell you I
would love to do that
what another topic for we'll get to the
final one which would be the Fermi
paradox is in addition to SETI classic
search for radio and also just beginning
laser another branch of SETI that's
getting more and more attention is the
techno signatures branch of SETI where
instead of looking for emissions we look
at things that might be masking the
emissions of the of stars in fact
there's you know still one oddball
candidate that has this odd variable
signature of solar emissions which is
not known to to meet up with any know
you know type of star and you know we
have things conceptually like the Dyson
shell which is an advanced enough
civilization builds a shell around its
star to harvest all the energy or a
lesser version the Dyson ring which is a
ring around its star which includes a
fair amount of the solar energy and so
the people are starting to look at four
techno signatures as well and so far
they haven't found any obviously but
there's you know at least one candidate
Tabitha's star I think it's called is
that what it's called yeah I think
that's it yeah so your thoughts on
techno signatures and what they might
help or hurt or help refine some of
these numbers in in your revised
equation yeah I I really think that's
the most likely way that we'll find a
Chetty civilization throughout the
throughout the galaxy or even in other
galaxies something that really hasn't
been done too much as look look for
communicating intelligent life so to
speak and other other galaxies because
there's two trillion galaxies in our
universe and we're only really looking
at one not really only looking at a
small small volume of that one galaxy
with traditional SETI so I'm a big fan
of looking for techno signatures now
people have done searches for Dyson
spheres in our own galaxy using the
infrared looking for basically anything
which is a bright in the infrared which
is unexpected and they haven't really
found anything there's really no good
candidates for that throughout our
galaxy it doesn't mean there aren't any
it's just that what we can see so far we
haven't really seen anything but that
might just be our own galaxy so if you
have so many galaxies throughout the
universe and you have some probability
of each galaxy having an advanced
technology then if you have enough
galaxies eventually you'll find a galaxy
which which has had a telogen life in it
for millions of years or so hundreds of
millions of years maybe and over that
period of time you can really do a lot I
mean you can really take over the galaxy
perhaps if you look at the way that
humans of our technology has expanded
them off the last season just a hundred
years just imagine what we could do if
that rate of technology continued for
for centuries or thousands of years or
millions of years it would just be
unimaginable
we can do so that I think is a really
good approach to looking for cities to
try to find these kind of alien art
archaeology archeoastronomy type things
throughout the throughout the universe
not just our own galaxy but but in other
galaxies now of course the question is
how do you find such a thing okay that's
that's really the trick what would these
you know technology signatures look like
even on a small scale within the galaxy
right would they just be Dyson spheres
but they'd just be stars that are all
sort of taken up by a sphere around them
where the light can't be seen at least
at least not in the optical but in the
only emits maybe an infrared or would it
be something else and it's really hard
to imagine what other things you could
do I mean you can imagine maybe they
move stars around maybe a galaxy has its
shape changed by these these
communicating civilizations I shouldn't
call communicating but these highly
technical civilizations in other
galaxies that can move stars around they
could have big regions of Dyson spheres
they can you know dim the whole galaxy
so they can they can power up their
civilization to do whatever whatever
they remember they need to do so I think
that's really a good a good thing to
look for them there's very little work
on that so people have done a little bit
looking in external galaxies for things
and I've actually done a project on this
myself recently with some students
looking for galaxies which deviate from
what we call scaling laws which is we
have a very tight relationship between
two quantities if the galaxy falls off
that relationship a good question is why
does it do that and one of the ways that
might do it is if there's something
altering the shape of the galaxy or
that's light and one of those things
could be an intelligence now it's one
very likely and in fact we didn't find
anything either
but it's possible and so people have
done this a little bit and this has been
going around I don't know a long time
now thirty years as probably as long as
people have been looking at this but it
has been the papers on this are very few
so there's big gaps with like five five
ten years where no one does anything but
there had been papers in the literature
for the last thirty years or so
where people have looked for these kind
of things in external galaxies but very
few people are working on that and SETI
the mainstream SETI is really looking
for these radio signals and maybe the
laser like you said coming from nearby
stars but I really think that we should
think more about
about looking for the kind of of of
alien signatures in the technology
overtaking part or all of it all of the
galaxy I'm really keen to see more
people do that yeah it does annoy the
hell out of me that have you know SETI
is to my mind the second most important
scientific question and unlike the first
most important question why is there
something rather than nothing we can
actually do something about it why is
the funding for SETI so small and you
know and as we talked about early on and
in your introduction why is it even
considered dangerous for a career in
astronomy or astrophysics to be a SETI
person it seems to me that if this is
such a huge question and we are actually
at the place where we're getting real
data why shouldn't this be funded at you
know hundreds of millions of dollars a
year right that that's a really good
question and and I thought a lot about
this and if you look at the history of
astronomy
there really are topics which are
somewhat taboo and and and discouraged
from people looking at even astrophysics
itself 150 years ago was considered to
be sort of a rogue thing and it wasn't
considered to be mainstream astronomy
astronomy back then was looking at star
positions and stuff like that and people
like August comp the philosopher the
French philosopher says said in the
beginning of the of the mid of the mid
19th century that we'll never know what
stars are made of these kind of things
but then people got spectrographs
started looking at stars and finally
yeah we know you know only a few years
after he said that people knew what
stars were made of and then you have
good a great example which i think is a
closest example to to SETI is cosmology
so for a very long time people who
thought about the idea of where did the
universe come from how did it start how
old is it all this stuff we're thought
to be y'all this is religion this is not
something that really a serious
scientist should look at but of course
now cosmology is ism is mainstream
astronomy it's a mainstream astrophysics
and it in some ways dominates the field
dominates the funding so SETI
is similar to that and you're absolutely
right that is one of the big questions
is it's really up there with with top
two or three questions you could
possibly ask in all science so why is it
not really well respected I think it's
simply because there's really no data
and that's sort of the same thing that
you had with the problem with cosmology
so certainly when wherever whenever we
do detect sort of life and I think that
will happen next decade or so I think we
will detect some kind of life on other
planets evidence for it but that life
will be very simple you know could be
analogous to plants or something like
that and it'll be found just by looking
at chemical elements and the atmospheres
of planets which is something that we
can do now quite quite easily although
not not to the ability to find evidence
for life but there are many new
telescopes coming online like James Webb
Space Telescope and these big new
telescopes that'll be 30 meters in
diameter on the ground that can can do
these federer scopic studies that can
find these elements and molecules and
the atmospheres of planets which can
tell us that perhaps or definitely
there's something going on which is
probably some form of life so I think
that will happen and that I think will
help a lot I think when we discover that
there'll be a lot more enthusiasm for
looking for intelligent life which will
be much harder to find glad you
mentioned that I was going to do that
which is that we're right on the verge
of either detecting or not
XO life by looking at the spectroscopy
of atmospheres of exoplanets and it's
possible it might be a dry hole I mean
you know it could be that we'll look at
several hundred habitable zone planet
atmospheres and find no life signature
which would you know start to fill in
one of the terms in the in the equation
in the original Drake Equation at least
which you guys chose to not get into
which I think it's a perfect transition
to the Drake Drake Equation to the Fermi
paradox right as people listen the show
know anyone with a scientific background
I always ask them about their view of
the Fermi paradox and to restate the
Fermi paradox it goes back to Los Alamos
at least this is the story that I've
heard or a bunch of young scientists
sitting at the lunch table we're
speculating oh there's got to be one
thousand smart intelligent civilizations
in the galaxy
yada yada and Enrico Fermi the famous
physicist came up to him and said where
are they
and if they're there where are they and
that's been the you know this question
the Fermi paradox how many are there and
if there really are some you know why
haven't we seen any sign of them and
there's arguments on both sides one and
essentially the Fermi paradox literature
tends to divide the analysis up into two
classes one that there aren't any and
two that they're there but for various
reasons we can't see them or they don't
want to see us and are actively avoiding
us in fact there's a great book called
if the universe is teeming with aliens
where is everybody by Stephen Webb which
goes through 75 different solutions to
the Fermi paradox and allocates them to
the different buckets you know and on
the on you know on the then it there is
no nobody there you know some of those
arguments are things like you know life
is exceedingly difficult or maybe not
life may be simple life is real simple
but what happened during the right
before the Cambrian explosion 540
million years ago where the template
that was laid down for all interesting
multicellular life of our sort and every
other interesting animal we know maybe
that was a really weird long shot or
maybe the development of chloroplasts
was an exceedingly long shot I think
we've learned now that's happened more
than once so that's one side then
there's a bunch of others you know on
the other side which is everybody gets
eaten by their a eyes within a hundred
years right or they this decide you know
the dark forest there and got to be
quiet there's bad guys out there so I'd
love to know your thoughts I mean if
you've been working in this space you
have to speculated about the Fermi
paradox if you have to put your flag on
the ground why haven't we detected
anybody yeah yeah it's a great question
right and yeah indeed I have thought a
lot about this so my solution to the
Fermi paradox is simply just the fact of
distances and rarity so if if these kind
of communicating
extraterrestrials are rare then they're
going to be far away and if they're far
away they're going to be really
difficult to detect and I would say a
third thing is perhaps the lifetime of
civilizations is not as long as we would
like to think they are that they're
actually not not very long so if you
have those three things and if you have
those three then then it's easy to solve
the Fermi paradox it's simply that there
are maybe a couple of civilizations in
our galaxy but they're really primitive
like us or close to us and they they're
so far away that we're not able to
detect them and they're not able to
detect us now you have to remember if
someone's looking at us and earth they
would never see that we have a technical
civilization unless they're about 100
light years away from us or closer if
they're further than that we still look
like a normal planet right we don't have
don't even barely have lights happening
lights are a bit or more than hundred
years but anyway you get the idea is
that our bubble of intelligence that's
projecting out into space is only about
a hundred light-years in radius which is
not very big for the size of the galaxy
and there's very likely to be
intelligent life within a hundred
light-years of us it's just very
unlikely those stars and we certainly
don't have it or us we definitely would
have noticed something by now I would
think so
by the fact that it's so rare and and so
far away it's unlikely to be unlikely to
be seen and then if you have a short
lifetime then also unlikely to be seeing
something because they don't last long
enough to develop a highly technical
civilization that could reproduce itself
on other stars or make robots that can
reproduce themselves and don't even need
the you know the biological alien
anymore but can survive for you know
perhaps tens of millions of years just
by self-replication and going throughout
the galaxy just you know and that
eventually would come to us but we
haven't seen that so that was that's
another sign that I think that this this
lifetime of these civilizations isn't
very long but it could be combined with
the rarity of them as well which is
another reason why I think looking at
external galaxies is another way of
trying to find to find these things
okay that's interesting so essentially
it's a density is low and the average
life time is short you run the math and
it's not surprising at all that we
haven't detected any but I think you're
yeah you were saying
in your paper that it's based on some
reasonable set of assumptions even
including your rather optimistic
assumption that life is easy that's
right it might well take thousands of
thousands of years to detect a a
civilization via that you know the
current level of effort in the in the
SETI space and obviously we've been
doing it for 50 or 60 years right okay
very good well this has been a wonderful
conversation on one of my very favorite
topics and I really want to thank you
for being here thank you very much for
the invitation I really really enjoyed
it alrighty thank you everybody
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]